DAN LI

EMAIL: d.li1@elsevier.com Google Scholar: Dan Li Linkedin: Dan Li

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My major research field is Information Retrieval (IR) and Text Mining (TM). I am also interested in Large Language Models (LLM) and Generative Artificial Intelligence (GenerativeAI). The following are topics I have been working on:

- TM: extreme multi-label classification, and its application in scientific texts and patent texts
- Semantic IR: dense retrieval, conversational search, question answering
- IR evaluation: test collection construction, high recall, technology-assisted review, crowdsourcing label denoising
- IR&NLP applications: painting generation for classical Chinese poems
- ML theories: machine learning, deep learning, language models, probabilistic graphical models, Gaussian process models, Bayesian optimization

EMPLOYMENT

Data Science, Research Content Operations, Elsevier

Amsterdam March 2022 - now

Data scientist

- Research: conducting research on IR and NLP, currently focusing on dense retrieval and extreme multilabel classification, and their automatic evaluation using ChatGPT
- Modelling: applying state-of-the-art models and developing novel models in IR and NLP to support Elsevier's information services
- Application: work with product teams to apply IR and NLP models to Elsevier's information services such as Topic Pages and Engineering Village

IRLab, University of Amsterdam

Amsterdam

ELLIS Postdoc

January 2021 – January 2022

- · Research: working with Prof. Dr. Maarten de Rijke on information retrieval
- · Management: working with Prof. Dr. Max Welling on the scientific management of ELLS Amsterdam

IRLab, University of Amsterdam

Amsterdam

PhD student

October 2016 - October 2020 • Supervisor & Promoter: Prof. Dr. Evangelos Kanoulas

• Thesis: Effective Collection Construction for Information Retrieval Evaluation and Optimization

Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd

Assistant software engineer

July 2011 - July 2013

• Role: developing driver software for industry-level routers

EDUCATION

University of Amsterdam (QS Ranking 55)	Amsterdam
PhD, Computer Science. Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Evangelos Kanoulas	October 2016 - October 2020
Tsinghua University (QS Ranking 17) Research exchange. Mentor: Prof. Dr. Yiqun Liu	Beijing February 2018 - March 2018
Dalian University of Technology (Shang Ranking 27)	Dalian, China
M.A., Linguistics and Applied Linguistics. Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Jingxiang Cao	September 2013 - July 2016
Dalian University of Technology	Dalian, China
B.Sc., Mathematics and Applied Mathematics	September 2007 - July 2011

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

• Li D., Yadav V., Zhu Z., Fard M., Afzal Z., Tsatsaronis G. (2023). Scalable Patent Classification with Aggregated Multi-View Ranking. EMNLP 2023.

Preprint	 	 	 	 	
- 1					

• Li D., Wang S., Zou J., Tian C., Nieuwburg E., Sun F., Kanoulas E. (2021). Paint4Poem: A dataset for artistic visualization of classical Chinese poems. ArXiv preprint.

Conferences/Journals

- Li D., de Rijke M. (2023). Extending Label Aggregation Models with a Gaussian Process to Denoise Crowdsourcing Labels. SIGIR 2023.
- Li D., Yadav V., Afzal Z., Tsatsaronis G. (2022). Unsupervised Dense Retrieval for Scientific Articles. Industry track of *EMNLP 2022*.
- Li D., Ren Z., Kanoulas E. (2021). CrowdGP: A Gaussian Process model for inferring relevance from crowd annotations. WWW 2021.
- Li D. (2021). Effective collection construction for information retrieval evaluation and optimization. *ACM SIGIR Forum.* PhD dissertation.
- Voskarides N., Li D., Ren P., Kanoulas E., de Rijke M. (2020). Query resolution for conversational search with limited supervision. SIGIR 2020.
- Li D., Zafeiriadis P., Kanoulas E. (2020). APS: An active PubMed search system for technology assisted reviews. SIGIR 2020.
- Li D., Kanoulas E. (2020). When to stop reviewing in technology-assisted reviews. ACM Transactions on Information Systems (TOIS).
- Zou J., Li D., Kanoulas E. (2018). Technology assisted reviews: Finding the last few relevant documents by asking yes/no questions to reviewers. SIGIR 2018.
- Inel O., Haralabopoulos G., Li D., Van Gysel C., Szlávik Z., Simperl E., Aroyo L. (2018). Studying topical relevance with evidence-based crowdsourcing. *CIKM 2018*.
- Li D., Kanoulas E. (2018). Bayesian optimization for optimizing retrieval systems. WSDM 2018.
- Zheng Y., Li D, Fan Z., Liu Y., Zhang M., Ma S. T-Reader: A multi-task deep reading comprehension model with self-attention mechanism. *Journal of Chinese Information Processing*.
- Li D., Kanoulas E. (2017). Active sampling for large-scale information retrieval evaluation. CIKM 2017.

Evaluation forums

- Kanoulas E., Li D., Azzopardi L., Spijker R. (2019). CLEF 2019 technology assisted reviews in empirical medicine overview. CLEF (Working Notes) 2019.
- Kanoulas E., Li D., Azzopardi L., Spijker R. (2018). CLEF 2018 technology assisted reviews in empirical medicine overview. CLEF (Working Notes) 2018.
- Kanoulas E., Li D., Azzopardi L., Spijker R. (2017). CLEF 2017 technology assisted reviews in empirical medicine overview. CLEF (Working Notes) 2017.
- Allan J., Harman D., Kanoulas E., Li D., Van Gysel C., Voorhees E. M. (2017). TREC 2017 common core track overview. TREC 2017.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Master thesis supervision	
• A comparative study of text to image generation methods for visualizing classical Chinese poems Zeyou Niu, Msc Artificial Intelligence	2022
 Automatic optimization techniques in machine learning pipelines Simon Appelt, Msc Artificial Intelligence 	2021
 Modelling task and worker correlation for crowdsourcing label aggregation Ioanna Sanida, Msc Artificial Intelligence 	2020
Statistical question classification Ruben Halfhide, Msc Data Science	2019
Bachelor thesis supervision	
Building a dataset for the visualization of classical Chinese poems Elisha A. Nieuwburg, Bsc Artificial Intelligence	2020
 De-noise large-scale poem-image pairs for poem-to-image generation Fengyuan Sun, Bsc Artificial Intelligence Cum laude (outstanding) bachelor thesis 	2020
 A representation of classical Chinese poetry for poem based image generation River Vaudrin, Bsc Artificial Intelligence 	2020

•	Image generation for classical Chinese poems	2020
	Nina M. van Liebergen, Bsc Artificial Intelligence Semantic visualization of classical Chinese poetry	2020
	Silvan Murre, Bsc Artificial Intelligence	2020
Teach	ing assistant	
•	Al Master Thesis Coaching Master course	2019
•	Text Retrieval and Mining Master course	2018
•	Data Mining bachelor course	2017
Aca	DEMIC ACTIVITIES	
Talks		
•	When to Stop Reviewing in Technology-assisted Reviews In SIGIR 2021	Online
•	CrowdGP: a Gaussian Process Model for Inferring Relevance from Crowd Annotations In WWW 2021	Online
•	APS: An Active PubMed Search System for Technology Assisted Review In SIGIR 2020	Online
•	Bayesian Optimization for Optimizing Retrieval Systems In WSDM 2018	Marina Del Rey
•	Active Sampling for Large-scale Information Retrieval Evaluation In CIKM 2017	Singapore
Orgar	nisation	
•	Technologically Assisted Reviews in Empirical Medicine 2017, 2018, 2019 (CLEF TAR) Co-organisation with Evangelos Kanoulas, Rene Spijker, and Leif Azzopardi Goal: CLEF TAR aims to evaluate high recall approaches for IR in medical don	Dublin, Avignon, Lugano nain.
	 Role: Tasks include constructing the datasets, running evaluation scripts, writi papers. 	ng part of the worknote
Partic	ipating challenges	
•	TREC Conversational Assistance Track 2019 (TREC CAST)	Gaithersburg
	 Co-participated with Nikos Voskarides, Pengjie Ren, Andreas Panteli from UvA IRI Role: We proposed a BERT-based model to resolve questions and to improve for conversational search systems. Our best model ranked 4 among 41 runs. 	re-ranking performance
•	Chinese Machine Reading Comprehension Challenge 2018	Beijing
	 Co-participated in the challenge with Yukun Zheng and Zhen Fan from Tsinghua Role: We proposed a neural machine reading comprehension model and p journal paper. 	
•	TREC Core Track 2017	Gaithersburg
	 Co-participated with Christophe Van Gysel and Evangelos Kanoulas from UvA IRL Role: We built a retrieval model using Indri and optimized the model hyper-pa Optimization. See the report. 	
Revie	wing	
•	EACL'20	
	CIKM'18/'19/'20	
	WWW'19/'20 WSDM'20	
	SIGIR'19/'20/'21/'22	

• TOIS, IRJ

PC member

- EACL'21
- CIKM'21/'22
- EMNLP'21/'22
- SIGIR'22/'23

Conference service

- Program chair of CLEF'23
- Proceeding chair of SIGIR'23

Fellowships

• Member of European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems (ELLIS): 2020 - now

AWARDS

- SIGIR Student Travel Grant, 2020
- CIKM Student Travel Grant, 2017
- Chinese National Scholarship for Graduate Students, top 1%, 2015

SKILLS

- Coding: Python, C, Java, Latex
- Machine Learning and Deep Learning tools: Scikit-learn, Pytorch, Tensorflow, Huggingface Transformer, Sentence Transformer, GPflow
- Language: Chinese (mother tongue), English (working language), Japanese (JLPT-N1 certificate), Dutch (Inburgering certificate), Thai (basic speaking and reading)